This is a thousand-year-old drawing of the brain.
هذا رسم للدماغ عمره ألف سنة
It's a diagram of the visual system.
انّه رسم تخطيطي للجهاز البصري
And some things look very familiar today.
وبعض الأمور تبدو مألوفة جداً اليوم.
Two eyes at the bottom, optic nerve flowing out from the back.
العينان في الجزء السفلي، العصب البصري يمتد خارجاً من الخلف.
There's a very large nose
وهناك أنف كبير جداً
that doesn't seem to be connected to anything in particular.
لا يبدو أنه يرتبط بأي شيء على وجه الخصوص.
And if we compare this
وإذا قارنّا هذا
to more recent representations of the visual system,
بنموذج أكثر حداثه للجهاز البصري
you'll see that things have gotten substantially more complicated
سترون أن الأمور أمست إلى حد كبير أكثر تعقيداً،
over the intervening thousand years.
على مر الألف سنه الماضيه.
And that's because today we can see what's inside of the brain,
وهذا لأنه يمكننا أن نرى اليوم ما هو داخل الدماغ،
rather than just looking at its overall shape.
بدلاً من مجرد النظر في شكله العام.
Imagine you wanted to understand how a computer works
تخيل أنك تريد أن تفهم كيفية عمل جهاز الحاسوب
and all you could see was a keyboard, a mouse, a screen.
وكل ما يمكنك أن تشاهده هو لوحة مفاتيح، فأرة، وشاشة.
You really would be kind of out of luck.
ستكون نوعاً ما غير محظوظ.
You want to be able to open it up, crack it open,
سوف ترغب أن تفتحه، أن تكسره،
look at the wiring inside.
انظروا إلى الأسلاك الموصوله في داخله.
And up until a little more than a century ago,
ومنذ حتى أكثر من قرن مضى،
nobody was able to do that with the brain.
لم يكن أحد قادراً على القيام بهذا مع الدماغ.
Nobody had had a glimpse of the brain's wiring.
لم يملك أحد أيّ فكرةٍ عن أسلاك الدماغ.
And that's because if you take a brain out of the skull
وذلك لأنك إذا أخرجت الدماغ من الجمجمة
and you cut a thin slice of it,
وقصصت شريحةً دقيقةً منه،
put it under even a very powerful microscope,
ووضعتها تحت مجهرقوي جداً،
there's nothing there.
فانك لن تجد فيها شيئاً.
It's gray, formless.
لونها رمادي، لا شكل لها.
There's no structure. It won't tell you anything.
لا قوام لها. لن تفيدك بشيء.
And this all changed in the late 19th century.
وتغيرهذا كله في أواخر القرن التاسع عشر.
Suddenly, new chemical stains for brain tissue were developed
فجأة، تمّ تطوير أصباغ كيميائيه لنسيج الدماغ
and they gave us our first glimpses at brain wiring.
وأعطتنا لمحات أوليّه عن توصيلات الدماغ.
The computer was cracked open.
إنفتح الكمبيوتر على مصراعيه.
So what really launched modern neuroscience
إذاً فالذي أسس علم الأعصاب الحديث فعليّاً
was a stain called the Golgi stain.
هو صبغه تدعى صبغة جولجي ( Golgi ).
And it works in a very particular way.
وهي تعمل بطريقة خاصة جداً.
Instead of staining all of the cells inside of a tissue,
بدلاً من تلوين كافة الخلايا داخل نسيج،
it somehow only stains about one percent of them.
فإنها بطريقه ما تلوّن واحد بالمئه من هذه الخلايا.
It clears the forest, reveals the trees inside.
كأنها تنظف الغابه وتكشف الأشجار في داخلها.
If everything had been labeled, nothing would have been visible.
لو كانت كل الأشياء ملوّنه لن يكون هناك شئٌ واضح.
So somehow it shows what's there.
إذاً بطريقة ما فإنها تظهر ما يوجد هناك.
Spanish neuroanatomist Santiago Ramon y Cajal,
عالم الأعصاب الإسباني "سانتياغو رامون ي كهال"،
who's widely considered the father of modern neuroscience,
الذي يعتبر عموما والد علم الأعصاب الحديث،
applied this Golgi stain, which yields data which looks like this,
استخدم صبغة جولجي التي تنتج صوراً كهذه
and really gave us the modern notion of the nerve cell, the neuron.
وأعطانا فعليّاً المفهوم الحالي للخلية العصبية، العصبون.
And if you're thinking of the brain as a computer,
وإذا كنت تتخيّل الدماغ كجهاز كمبيوتر،
this is the transistor.
فهذا هو الترانزستور.
And very quickly Cajal realized
وسرعان ما أدرك "كهال"
that neurons don't operate alone,
أن الخلايا العصبية لا تعمل منفرده،
but rather make connections with others
لكنها تنشئ صِلات مع غيرها
that form circuits just like in a computer.
مما يشكل دوائراً تماماً كالكمبيوتر
Today, a century later, when researchers want to visualize neurons,
اليوم، وبعد قرن، عندما يريد الباحثون معاينة الخلايا العصبية،
they light them up from the inside rather than darkening them.
فإنهم يضيؤنها من الداخل بدلاً من تعتيمها.
And there's several ways of doing this.
وهناك عدة طرق للقيام بذلك.
But one of the most popular ones
لكن واحده من أكثرها شيوعاً
involves green fluorescent protein.
تشمل البروتين الأخضر المضيء.
Now green fluorescent protein,
الآن، البروتين الأخضر المضيء
which oddly enough comes from a bioluminescent jellyfish,
وهو، من الغرابة بمكان، يأتي من قنديل البحر المضيء
is very useful.
هو مفيد جداً.
Because if you can get the gene for green fluorescent protein
لأنه إذا امكنك الحصول على الوحده الوراثيّه للبروتين الأخضر المضيء
and deliver it to a cell,
ووضعها داخل خلية
that cell will glow green --
فسوف تتوهج تلك الخلية خَضاراً --
or any of the many variants now of green fluorescent protein,
أو بلون آخر من ألوان البروتين المضيء المتنوّعه حاليّاً
you get a cell to glow many different colors.
يمكنك جعل الخلية تتوهج بألوان مختلفة متعدده.
And so coming back to the brain,
ولنعود الآن للدماغ،
this is from a genetically engineered mouse called "Brainbow."
هذا مأخوذ من فأر معدّل وراثياً يسمى برينبو (دماغ قزحي)
And it's so called, of course,
وسمّي كذلك بالطبع
because all of these neurons are glowing different colors.
لأن كل من هذه الخلايا العصبية متوهجة بألوان مختلفه
Now sometimes neuroscientists need to identify
في بعض الأحيان يحتاج علماء الأعصاب لتحديد
individual molecular components of neurons, molecules,
مكوّنات جزيئيه فرديّه من العصبون، جزيئات
rather than the entire cell.
بدلاً من الخلية بأكملها
And there's several ways of doing this,
وهناك عدة طرق للقيام بذلك
but one of the most popular ones
لكن واحدة من أكثرها شعبية
involves using antibodies.
تنطوي على استخدام الأجسام المضادة
And you're familiar, of course,
وأنتم تعرفون بالطبع
with antibodies as the henchmen of the immune system.
أن الأجسام المضادة هي عصابة النظام المناعي
But it turns out that they're so useful to the immune system
ولكن اتضح أنها مفيدة جداً للنظام المناعي
because they can recognize specific molecules,
لأنها قادره على تمييز جزيئات محددة
like, for example, the coat protein
مثلاً، وعلى سبيل المثال، البروتين المشفّر
of a virus that's invading the body.
لفيروس يغزو الجسم.
And researchers have used this fact
وقد استخدم الباحثون هذه الحقيقة
in order to recognize specific molecules inside of the brain,
حتى يتمكنوا من تمييز جزيئات محددة في داخل الدماغ
recognize specific substructures of the cell
لتمييز مكونات فرعيّه محدده في الخليه
and identify them individually.
والتعرف عليها كلٌّ على حده
And a lot of the images I've been showing you here are very beautiful,
وكثير من الصور التي عرضتها لكم هنا جميلة جداً
but they're also very powerful.
لكنّها أيضاً قوية جداً
They have great explanatory power.
لديها قوة تفسيرية هائلة
This, for example, is an antibody staining
هذا، على سبيل المثال، صباغ بالاجسام المضاده
against serotonin transporters in a slice of mouse brain.
ضد ناقلات السيروتونين في شريحة من دماغ فأر
And you've heard of serotonin, of course,
ولابدّ أنكم سمعتم بالسيروتونين، بطبيعة الحال
in the context of diseases like depression and anxiety.
في سياق أمراض مثل الاكتئاب والقلق.
You've heard of SSRIs,
قد سمعتم بال SSRIs
which are drugs that are used to treat these diseases.
وهي الأدوية التي تستخدم لعلاج هذه الأمراض
And in order to understand how serotonin works,
ومن أجل فهم كيفية عمل السيروتونين،
it's critical to understand where the serontonin machinery is.
من المهم أن نعرف مكان آليات السيروتونين،
And antibody stainings like this one
و الصبغ بالاجسام المضاده مثل هذا
can be used to understand that sort of question.
يمكن استخدامه لفهم هذا النوع من الأسئله
I'd like to leave you with the following thought:
أود أن اترككم مع الفكره الآتيه:
Green fluorescent protein and antibodies
البروتين الأخضر المضيء والأجسام المضادة
are both totally natural products at the get-go.
كلاهما منتج طبيعي تماماً منذ البدء
They were evolved by nature
تطورت من الطبيعه
in order to get a jellyfish to glow green for whatever reason,
حتى تمكّن قنديل البحر من أن يتوهج أخضراً لسبب ما
or in order to detect the coat protein of an invading virus, for example.
أو بهدف الكشف عن الشفره الوراثيّه لفيروس معدي مثلاً
And only much later did scientists come onto the scene
وبعد فتره طويله ظهر العلماء في الساحه
and say, "Hey, these are tools,
وقالوا : " مهلاً، إنّ هذه أدوات،
these are functions that we could use
هي وسائل يمكننا تسخيرها
in our own research tool palette."
ضمن مجموعة أدوات البحث العلمي".
And instead of applying feeble human minds
وبدلاً من استخدام العقول البشرية الضعيفة
to designing these tools from scratch,
لتصميم هذه الأدوات من لا شيء،
there were these ready-made solutions right out there in nature
كانت تلك الحلول الجاهزه موجوده أصلاً في الطبيعه
developed and refined steadily for millions of years
طُوِّرت و صُقلت بتوءده عبر ملايين السنين
by the greatest engineer of all.
على يد أعظم مهندس على الاطلاق.
Thank you.
شكرا.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)